Okay, welcome back.
The next section is going to deal with
chronic obstructive pulmonary disease,
and the idea here is that these are chronic diseases
that obviously affect the lung,
and that the key underlying premise in all of these diseases,
and there's going to be four total,
is that we have obstruction.
Now, what do we mean by obstruction?
It is an obstruction to getting air out of the lung.
That's the notion that we have to carry in the back of our mind
when we're thinking about these diseases.
In each of these disorders, there will be an obstruction
to getting air out of the lung.
Airway obstruction is the hallmark of these diseases,
as I've already highlighted to you,
and when you think about airway obstruction,
you should recognize that this airway obstruction in the patient
is clinically going to manifest with changes in spirometry.
Now, spirometry is the way by which we measure lung volumes,
and if you go back to normal physiology,
you'll recall that there are a series of measurements
that we can obtain from spirometry.
It's not the purpose of this discussion
to go into a detailed talk about spirometry,
but what I would like to highlight
are the key take-homes that you have to know,
especially in the context of disease,
from your understanding of spirometry.
So let's begin with one idea here,
and that is that if we've got airway obstruction,
and the problem is getting air out of the lung,
then the forced vital capacity will go down.
What's the forced vital capacity?
This is the amount of air that you can blow out
when you breathe all the way in
and then blow out as much as you can.
So it's a maximal expiration.
Otherwise stated, if you want to think about it another way,
if I asked you to blow out candles on a birthday cake,
you would use the FVC.
You would breathe in as deeply as possible
and then blow out as much as you could.
So in this particular set of diseases,
because there's obstruction,
the forced vital capacity,
the amount of air that you could blow out maximally,
is going to go down.
In addition, what's also going to go down is the FEV1.
The FEV1 is the forced expiratory volume,
and that's the amount of volume that you can get out
in a one-second period, hence the designation 1.
And so this represents the amount of air
that comes out of the lung with a forced expiration
in the very first second of that expiration.
This will also go down,
but it will go down more than the forced vital capacity.
And that's actually very important to understand,
because that translates in a key finding
that almost defines the disease,
which is that there is a decrease
in the FEV1 to FVC ratio.
It's probably easier to understand this
with a couple numbers,
so let's just plug in some numbers
to understand what I'm talking about.
Let me remind you that your normal forced vital capacity,
the normal amount of air that you could blow out
in a maximal expiration,
is about 5 liters.
That's the normal.
Now, of that 5 liters, about 4 liters
is what is removed within the first one second.
So that ratio, 4 over 5, is about 80%,
and that's the normal.
Now, let's say that a patient has COPD.
Well, obviously, this number is gonna go down,
and this number is really gonna go down,
and that's gonna change the percentage
so that the ratio decreases, for example.
In a patient with COPD,
we might expect that the forced vital capacity
goes down by one liter to four liters,
and we would expect that the FEV1
would significantly decrease from four liters
to maybe two liters,
and so now that ratio is 50%,
and so these patients have had a decrease
in their FEV1 to FVC ratio,
and that's a very important
high-yield physiology association for COPD.
It's very important to be aware of.
An additional finding in COPD
will be that the total lung capacity
will be increased.
The total lung capacity
is the total amount of air
that you can have within the lung
at the maximally,
and so that total lung capacity
is going to be increased
because there's gonna be air trapping.
If you can't get air out of the lung,
some air will be trapped in the lung,
and so the total amount of air
present within the lung maximally
will actually increase,
and that's the total lung capacity.
Generally speaking,
if you wanna know,
if you wanna think about this
with some numbers,
the normal total lung capacity
is about seven liters,
and in COPD,
it goes up to about eight liters.
So here's some very high-yield physiology
tie-in for this particular discussion.
Now, the very first of these diseases
is called chronic bronchitis.
Chronic bronchitis is interesting
because it's defined clinically.
Basically, the notion is
that the patient has a productive cough,
and that productive cough
lasts at least three months
over a minimum of two years.
This cough is so productive
that when the patient comes to you,
they will tell you
that they are coughing up cups of mucus,
tons and tons of mucus.
Some patients will come to you
saying they cough up buckets of mucus.
That's how much mucus
is produced in these patients.
Now, the next question would be why.
What drives this disease?
Basically, it's a smoking-related disease.
To understand this,
you actually have to understand
a little bit of normal histology,
so let me take you back one step.
Here is the lumen of the bronchus,
and this is chronic bronchitis,
so it would involve large airways
like the bronchus,
so this is the lumen of the bronchus,
and then you're well aware
that the epithelium that lines this region
is called respiratory epithelium,
and remember that respiratory epithelium
is pseudostratified,
which means that some nuclei are high
and some nuclei are low,
and it's called pseudostratified
because all the cells
really do touch the basement membrane.
So that's pseudostratified columnar,
the cells are tall,
ciliated, the cells have cilia,
epithelium,
and again,
all of these cells
sit on a basement membrane,
and that's the epithelium.
Underneath that epithelium
is a lamina propria,
and recall that
in the lamina propria,
you have very large caliber
blood vessels,
venules basically,
and these venules,
they bring warm blood
into the region,
which then allows the air
to be warmed
before it goes down
to the bottom of the lung
for exchange,
and so that's the lamina propria,
and then underneath
the lamina propria,
you have something called
the submucosa,
and remember that
the submucosa contains glands
and there's two types of glands.
One gland is called
the serous gland
and that serous gland
produces watery fluid
that helps to humidify the air.
The watery fluid
goes up here
and then humidifies the air
before it goes down
into the lung,
and of course,
the purpose of humidifying the air
is that you don't want
to turn the lung
into a dry sponge.
At the same time,
there are mucinous glands
and the mucinous glands
produce mucus-like fluid,
which then goes
and lines the epithelial surface,
and that mucusy fluid
acts as a filter
for particles
as you're breathing in
because you don't want
the pollution and junk
from the outside ear
to actually come down
into the lung.
So that's the purpose
of the mucinous glands.
And then, of course,
underneath the submucosa
in a large airway
like the bronchus
would be cartilage.
Now, let me just remind you
that normally,
the ratio of these glands here
to the entire thickness
of the wall
is less than 40%,
i.e.,
basically,
the mucinous glands
take up about 40%
or less
of the thickness
of the wall.
Now, let's imagine
that there's a patient
that smokes.
If they smoke,
they're going to be bringing
in a ton of pollutants,
a ton of foreign particles
into their lung.
And in response,
the lung is going
to try to respond
to deal with all
that foreign material
by increasing
the amount of mucus produced.
So if you need
to increase
the amount of mucus produced,
you're going to undergo
hyperplasia
and hypertrophy
of these mucinous glands.
So as we get
excess mucinous glands
because of the smoking,
then these excess
mucinous glands
are going to take over,
why don't we say this,
the excess mucinous glands
are going to increase
in thickness
relative to the overall
thickness of the wall.
And so the mucinous glands,
their thickness
will become greater
than 50%
of the overall wall.
And that's important
because that's called
the read index.
The read index measures
the thickness
of the mucinous glands
relative to the entire
thickness of the wall.
And in chronic bronchitis,
it becomes greater
than 50%.
Now what's also important
to note is that
if we've got all
of these mucinous glands
and they're producing
a ton of mucus,
guess where all that mucus
is going to go?
Into the lumen.
And guess how the patient
is going to get rid of it?
Well some of it
is going to be coughed up
which is then going to
create the chronic bronchitis
with the productive cough
that lasts at least
three months
over a minimum
of two years.
And at the same time,
some of the mucus
is also going to go back
and it's going to
plug the airways.
And when it plugs
the airways,
there's going to be trapping
and there's going to be
an obstruction
to getting air
out of the lung.
With all of that background,
now you can understand
the disease.
So what did I say?
I told you that it is
highly associated
with smoking.
That should make sense.
At the same time,
I tell you in your text,
and go back
and read the text now,
there's hypertrophy
of the bronchial mucinous glands.
This increases the thickness
of the mucus glands
relative to the overall
bronchial wall thickness
and the read index
becomes greater than 50%.
Again, normally
it should be less than 40%.
Let's illustrate that again
with a real histologic image.
What I've tried to do
in this image
is I've tried to capture
the entire wall thickness.
So we start up here
at the very top.
That's the respiratory epithelium
in the upper right-hand
side of this slide.
This is sitting
on a basement membrane.
Underneath the basement membrane
is a lamina propria
which contains dilated venules
which basically bring in
warm blood
in order to humidify the air.
These are the mucinous glands
from here
all the way here.
You can see
all these little circular spaces
that are lined
by mucinous cells
and these cells
basically produce mucus
which goes up
and then goes out
into the luminal space.
Now, it's important to note
that normally
the thickness
of these mucinous glands
should be about
40% or less
of the entire wall thickness.
Here's the cartilage down here.
If I look at this
entire wall thickness
up here
and I ask you
a simple question.
What percentage
of that thickness
is taken over
by the mucinous glands
I think you would agree
with me
that it's certainly
greater than 50%
and so
thickness of the mucinous glands
is an increase
in the read index
which is one of the
classic findings
in chronic bronchitis.
Now, these patients
with chronic bronchitis
are going to present
with a productive cough
but that makes sense
because they're making
a ton of mucus
and that ton of mucus
is going to come out
as a cough.
So that's the
classic clinical feature
and there's no
rocket science here.
Another important finding
is that they're going
to get an increase
in the PaCO2
and a decrease
in the PaO2
and that's going
to present a cyanosis
or blue discoloration
in the patient.
Now, in order to understand
that we can probably
go back a step
and remind ourselves
that the goal
of the lung
is to generate
a partial pressure
of oxygen
in this alveolar airspace
of P big AO2
and that P big AO2
produces a pressure
that squeezes oxygen
into the blood vessels
and when it squeezes
oxygen into the blood vessels
that creates a P small aO2
within these blood vessels.
So, that's the normal.
Now, of course,
you don't want to have
carbon dioxide
or as soon as you pick up
any carbon dioxide
in the alveolar space
you don't want to keep it there
you want to blow it out
because there is a limit
to the amount of pressure
that you can generate
within this region
and you want all
of that pressure
to be pressure of oxygen.
If you start putting
carbon dioxide here
so that you now generate
a P ACO2
that's significant
that increase in P ACO2
will automatically
decrease the P AO2
and that decrease
in P AO2
will mean that there's
less pressure
to squeeze the oxygen
across that barrier
into the blood
and so the P small aO2
will also decrease.
And so basically
this is the summary
of what's going to happen
lab-wise.
The P big ACO2
will go up
along with the P small aCO2
and the P big AO2
will go down
along with the P small aO2.
So that's the summary
of how the patients
become cyanotic
and why they get
these particular lab findings.
Another important thing
to be familiar with
is that there's an increased
risk of infection.
Here's a general
pathology principle.
Anytime you have a tube
and you block it
you're going to get
an infection behind
that block.
So for example
patients who have BPH
they're not able
to get urine out
very well
and so the urine piles up
in the bladder
and there's an increased
risk of bladder infection
in those patients.
Similarly here
if you've got airways
and you can imagine
that the airways
as they branch
if there's mucus plugging
you're going to get
infection behind that block
and so there's an increased
risk of infection
in these patients.
And the final thing
to be aware of
is that there's a risk
of core pulmonale
in these patients.
So what's core pulmonale?
That requires a little bit
of understanding
of physiology.
Now recall that
the blood vessels
in the lung
they are designed
to recognize
that if there is
a lack of oxygen
in a particular region
of the lung
that they should actually
clamp down
to shut down
that region
and instead
shunt the blood
in another direction.
Let's just take
a simple example.
Let's say a patient
has pneumonia.
It's in the left upper lobe.
If they've got
a left upper lobe pneumonia
there's really not much
oxygen getting in there
because the lung
is basically loaded
with pus
and inflammatory debris.
So in response
what the capillaries
of the alveolar air sacs do
actually this happens
at the level
of the arterioles
but what the arterioles
do is they squeeze down
to decrease the amount
of blood going
to the left upper lobe
and instead
blood will be shunted
to other parts
of the lung
with the hope
that that blood
will be able
to meet oxygen
and to be able
to carry out
the exchange
that is the purpose
of the lung.
So that makes sense
and that's very good
because if I've got
an upper lobe pneumonia
in the left lobe
I don't want my blood
going there
looking for oxygen
and instead
I'd like to send it
to another part
of the lung.
But imagine
that if you have
a disease
where you're not
oxygenating properly
and so you start
clamping down
and every area
of the lung
clamps down
thinking that
blood should go
to another part
of the lung
not knowing
that there's disease
in another part
of the lung
everybody's clamping
down
and trying to send
the blood
in a different direction
but there's disease
throughout the entire lung
so that's a problem
and all of that
clamping down
of the blood vessels
has to be dealt
with by the right heart
the right heart
is going to have
to pump against
all of that
high blood pressure
and so that's
going to result
in initially
right ventricular
hypertrophy
and eventually
the patients
will fail
the right heart
and that's called
core pulmonale
so that's a very
high yield
sort of
paradigm
to be familiar
with
so emphysema
is the next
of the chronic
obstructive pulmonary
diseases
and in this
particular case
there's destruction
of the alveolar
air sacs
now remember
from your normal
histology
that the lung
is sort of like
an upside down
tree
so that if this
is the main stem
bronchus
and then the bronchus
kind of branches
off into these
bronchioles
and eventually
the bronchioles
branch off into
terminal bronchioles
and eventually
you produce these
alveolar air sacs
which is where
the exchange occurs
now
I call it an upside down
tree because
this is sort of
the trunk up here
and then you've got
all these branches
and eventually
the leaves are like
the air sacs
they're sort of
tiny little leaves
at the very tips
of the branches
and so what happens
in emphysema
is that you get
destruction
of these alveolar
air sacs
and as you get
destruction of the
alveolar air sacs
that results
in a chronic
obstructive pulmonary
disease
now you could ask
example you could
stop me here
and you could say
well what are you
talking about
you said
that these are
obstructive diseases
I don't see any
obstruction in this
disease
that's true
you don't see any
anatomic obstruction
and you don't really
see any
mucus plugging
or anything
of that nature
which would create
an obstruction
but the obstruction
here is a little
more physiologic
and that's going to be
important to understand
because it ties into
a few high yield
principles
so let me remind
you of a couple
things
first of all
what's happening
in this disease
is you've got
you know
you've got all
these alveolar
air sacs
at the very
distal portion
of the lung
and these alveolar
air sacs are like
tiny balloons
they fill up
with air
and as soon as
they fill up
with air
they immediately
snap back
due to their
elastic recoil
and then they
blow the air out
so you breathe in
and you fill up
the balloon
and then you relax
and then the air
is squeezed out
so first of all
imagine if we lost
this elastic recoil
because we destroyed
some of the walls
of the lung
then instead of having
a bunch of little balloons
what we'd really have
is one big shopping bag
and that shopping bag
is not going to have
good elastic recoil
and so you're not going
to be able to get
air out of the lung
very well
I mean just take
a simple example
if I gave you a balloon
and asked you to blow it up
and then you let go of it
it's going to shoot air
back in your face
but if I give you
a shopping bag
and blow it up
and then ask you to
let go of it
air is not going
to shoot back
in your face
so instead of having
a bunch of little balloons
it's as if the lung
develops a bunch
of big shopping bags
so that's one reason
why they're not able
to get air out
i.e. they're obstructed
from getting air out
a second reason
why they're obstructed
from getting air out
is the following
and this requires
a little bit of
physiology
so let me take you
back a step
and just remind you
the lung
is an upside down tree
and you've got
this main stem bronchus
and then you've got
all these branches
and then you've
sort of got
all these little balloons
now as you've got
millions and millions
of these air sacs
and as you breathe out
you're going to
accelerate air
up through this system
and as you accelerate
air up through this system
you're really going to
kind of narrow
the number of tubes
so that eventually
you shoot all the air
through one large caliber
one large caliber
conducting airway
now that
as you're blowing
all that air through
that creates
a significant amount
of acceleration
of the air
and you can imagine
that as air
is being shot out
this way
it's also going
to drag
on the wall
of the tube
and when it drags
on the wall
of the tube
there's going to be
a tendency
to cause that tube
to collapse
now up here
in the larger airways
you have cartilage
in the wall
and the reason
for having cartilage
in the wall
is because
you want that
airway
to be able
to remain open
when you're
breathing out
and accelerating air
across that tube
so the cartilage
helps to keep
that wall open
as air
is shooting up
out through it
again
you don't want
that wall
to collapse
now down here
remember that
the defining
distinction
between a bronchus
and a bronchial
is a lack of cartilage
there's no cartilage
in the bronchioles
the bronchioles
instead
the way they stay open
is that there are
a bunch of alveolar air sacs
for example
here and here
why don't I clear this
and draw this again
you know
this is a bronchial now
and the way
the bronchial stays open
is that you've got
these air sacs
and the air sacs
have elastic recoil
and that elastic recoil
actually pulls
open these walls
now normally
when I breathe out
I'm going to accelerate
air across this tube
when I accelerate air
across this tube
I'm going to actually
create a force
on the wall
of the tube
that's going to suck
that tube closed
however
these air sacs
are going to keep
that tube open
because they have
elastic recoil
and they're pulling
at the tube
keeping it open
let's imagine
that I destroy
these walls
so that now
I don't have
that elastic recoil
well when I lose
as I shoot air up
this way
I'm going to actually
drag the wall
along with it
and when I drag
the wall along with it
boom
this wall is going to close
and when this wall
closes
that's going to result
in obstruction
this is a very high yield
principle to understand
because it goes back
to normal physiology
it ties in a little bit
of histology
and it also reminds you
of the reason
why there's obstruction
basically
the patients
they get collapse
of the small airways
due to loss
of the elastic recoil
of the alveolar air sacs
let's go back
and read together
so what do I say
I say that emphysema
is a destruction
of the alveolar air sacs
there's loss
of elastic recoil
and collapse
of the small airways
and this leads
to air trapping
so I've already
explained that
here's what a picture
of emphysema
looks like
but here you can
clearly see
that you're seeing
all these spongy holes
within the lung
and that's because
those normal
little tiny balloons
have been converted
to quote unquote
shopping bags
and so this spongy
appearance
to the lung
this porous spongy
appearance
is classic
for emphysema
now going one step
further
we can look at this
histologically
and we'll see
the same process
let's just take
for example here
the bottom left hand
corner of the screen
let's say that
that's a normal air sac
so there are a few
rare normal air sacs
in this picture
now look at these air sacs
these are way too dilated
these are huge
dilated air sacs
and that's because
we've lost
alveolar air sac
and so we've converted
those tiny balloons
into shopping bags
so why does this occur
why do patients
get emphysema
and to understand this
you have to recognize
that there's a
in emphysema
there's an imbalance
between proteases
and antiproteases
that's what really
causes the disease
so what does that mean
let me just remind you
that every time
in the lung
particularly the mucus
within the lung
and that allows us
to keep whatever
whatever goes down
into the very
distal portions
of the lung
clean
now when you get
to the bottom of the lung
you don't have those
defense mechanisms
so the only way
by which we can
defend ourselves
at the very bottom
of the lung
is a cell called
the alveolar macrophage
it sort of eats things
that might happen
to get way down
at the very bottom
of the lung
it's not common
for particles to get down
there but it is possible
now on occasion
there will be some things
that will come down
to that part of the lung
the macrophages
will eat them
and when the macrophages
eat them
that induces a little bit
of inflammation
so otherwise stated
it's common
to have some degree
of inflammation
present
within the
alveolar air sacs
now that little bit
of inflammation
in the alveolar air sacs
is going to produce
proteases
that's a byproduct
of inflammation
that would be damaging
to the lung
but
but the body
produces a protein
that protects against proteases
and those are called
the anti-proteases
the most important
of which
is one called
alpha-1 antitrypsin
so otherwise stated
we constantly have
a small level
of inflammation
ongoing
within the
alveolar air sacs
that small level
of inflammation
results in the
production of proteases
which are a
byproduct of inflammation
causing tissue damage
in order to protect
ourselves
against those proteases
we have anti-proteases
the most important
of which
is alpha-1 antitrypsin
now this
normally exists
in a balance
so that the proteases
and the anti-proteases
are present
in balance
so that whatever proteases
are produced
we have enough
anti-proteases
to handle those
in emphysema
the problem
is either
an over production
of proteases
or a decreased production
of anti-proteases
now there's basically
two classic diseases
that give you emphysema
and each one
and what each one
covers a particular
aspect of this
paradigm
for example
one group of patients
and the most common
group of patients
to develop emphysema
are those that have
a tremendous amount
of inflammation
going on
in the distal portions
of the lung
and guess who those
patients are
smokers
smoking is the most
common cause of
emphysema
smokers bring a ton
of garbage into their
lung
there's a ton of
protease activity
overrides
the anti-protease
activity
and these patients
then develop
emphysema
because those proteases
destroy the alveolar
air sacs
so that's one group
of patients
that develops emphysema
the second group
of patients
that develop emphysema
are those patients
when you consider
this balance
of proteases
and anti-proteases
the second group
of patients
are those patients
that have decreased
anti-proteases
and the classic disease
which is relatively
rare clinically
but is very common
on examinations
is where patients
have an alpha-1
anti-trypsin deficiency
now if patients
don't have good
alpha-1 anti-trypsin
floating around
in the blood
then they won't
be able to protect
against the protease
damage that occurs
normally
so over time
there's a chance
that they could
develop emphysema
so that's the second
disease that's going
to result in emphysema
and that's alpha-1
anti-trypsin deficiency
now let's read together
what do I say
in the book
I say smoking
is the most common
cause of emphysema
that I've already
explained
and it results
in sentry acinar
emphysema
which is more severe
in the upper lobes
this requires
a little bit of
explanation
now what is
sentry acinar
emphysema
so why don't I
take a step back
and remind you
that there are two
major categories
of emphysema
there's a sentry acinar
pan-acinar emphysema
in order to understand
this concept
you need to understand
the acinous
so let's go back here
and remind ourselves
that the functional unit
of the lung
is called the acinous
remember that we get
a terminal bronchial
and the terminal bronchial
eventually opens up
into the alveolar air sacs
so this is sort of
the functional unit
of the lung
this whole thing
that I'm outlining here
that's called the acinous
now let's pretend
that a patient
is a smoker
so that you know
the smoke is coming down
the central airway
eventually branches
and comes into the
terminal bronchial
obviously there would be
multiple branches here
I'm just simplifying this image
eventually comes into
the terminal bronchial
and then hits the acinous
let me ask you
a very simple question
which part of this acinous
is going to be
most hit by the smoke
of course
the central part
of the acinous
and so guess
what type of
emphysema
smokers are going to get
sentry acinar emphysema
very easy
and of course
the other one is called
panacinar
and panacinar means
that you disrupt
the entire acinous
and the patients
who get panacinar
emphysema
are those who are
alpha 1 antitrypsin
deficient
but the way I remember this
I only remember the
smoking related
is sentry acinar
because it makes sense to me
and then I know
the other one is panacinar
and so I associate that
with alpha 1 antitrypsin
now one more important
principle
and that is
that patients who smoke
not only do they get
sentry acinar emphysema
but it's also more severe
in the upper lobes
but again there's no
rocket science here
if I give you a match
and I blow it out
which way is the smoke
going to go
it's going to go up
obviously
and so when a patient smokes
guess which way the smoke
is going to go
when it goes in the lung
it's going to go up
it's one way to remember this
right
so these patients are going to get
sentry acinar emphysema
that's more severe
in the upper lobes
so that should be now
fairly easy to understand
and let's read together
I say that smoking is the most common cause of emphysema
it results in sentry acinar emphysema
that is more severe in the upper lobes
then I say in your text
that alpha 1 antitrypsin deficiency
is a rare cause of emphysema
it results in panacinar emphysema
more common in the lower lobes
again it's opposite of smoking
we're going to see it more commonly
in the lower lobes
now here's one more point
to be discussed
and that's that patients
who have alpha 1 antitrypsin deficiency
may also develop liver cirrhosis
what I want to remind you
is that in alpha 1 antitrypsin deficiency
the deficiency is that
the protein is not in the blood
however the liver
is still making the protein
and what happens in this particular disease
is that alpha 1 antitrypsin
is produced by the liver
but the mutation results
in a misfolding of the protein
so that the protein begins to accumulate
within the endoplasmic reticulum
of hepatocytes
and when it accumulates
within the endoplasmic reticulum
of hepatocytes
it begins to pile up
in the liver cells
and eventually damages
the cells
resulting in cirrhosis
and that's why liver cirrhosis
may be present
and here's the high yield
way by which examiners
like to ask this
so these are all hepatocytes
this is a biopsy of the liver
and you can clearly see
that for example
in this hepatocyte
there are these round
purple or pink colored globules
and so these purple or pink colored globules
these actually represent alpha 1 antitrypsin
that's building up in the hepatocyte
very high yield picture for examinations
what I'd like to also remind you of
is that these globules
they are PAS positive
PAS is a special stain
that we use in histology
and they're PAS positive
and examiners like you to know that as well
so pink PAS positive globules
and that's all the key summaries
for this particular slide
now one more thing
that we have to be familiar with
and that is the genetics
behind alpha 1 antitrypsin deficiency
let me remind you
that alpha 1 antitrypsin gene
comes in multiple alleles
the most common allele
or subtype is called PIM
so that most patients
actually have PIM
and then another copy of PIM
and most people
are actually possessing this allele
and this is the normal allele
and so there's no problem
the mutations are multiple
there are many many many mutations
however the most common clinical mutation
to be aware of
is the PIZ allele
PIZ is going to result
in a mutation
such that you get malformation
or misfolding of the protein
I should say
and the protein is going to accumulate
in the endoplasmic reticulum
alright
board point
endoplasmic reticulum
now
one possibility
is that the patients
could be heterozygates
they could have one normal allele
the M allele
and one abnormal allele
the Z allele
these patients are usually
asymptomatic
but there will be
a decreased circulating level
of alpha 1 antitrypsin
that's because
they're only producing
half of the normal
these patients usually are fine
however
if the patient smokes
there's a really high risk
for the development
of emphysema
and so the way by which
we would treat these patients
is to make sure
make sure
that they don't smoke
so that's the
the PIMZ heterozygates
now it's also possible
for a patient to have
PIZZ
i.e. they're homozygous
for the mutation
if they're homozygous
these are the classic patients
who get
panacinar emphysema
and cirrhosis
so this is the classic patient
who's going to get
panacinar emphysema
plus cirrhosis
and i've already explained
the cirrhosis to you
now clinically
the features are going
to be the following
the patients will have
dyspnea
shortness of breath
they're going to have
cough but they won't
produce sputum
this is not chronic
bronchitis
so they're not going to
be coughing up
a ton of mucus
the patients are going
to have prolonged
expiration with pursed lips
this is very very
very high yield
so again when you think
about this
if this is a small airway
and you know that the
problem is that they lost
the elastic recoil
that was holding this
airway open
because of the emphysema
so that now when they
accelerate air
they're also going to be
dragging this wall
and this wall is going
to collapse shut
imagine if the patient
is creating pursed lips
so that they increase
the back pressure
from above
then that's going to
create a little bit
of back pressure here
and that back pressure
is going to force
these walls open
so by creating a little
bit of back pressure
and forcing the walls
open
the patient will then
be able to get air
out
albeit slowly
but they'll at least
be able to get air out
and so what these patients
do clinically
is that they
prolong their expiration
and they purse their lips
so that they generate
a little bit of back
pressure
which will then
allow air
to be able to move
in and out
and so they can maintain
their oxygenation
but they have to breathe
in this funny way
and so that's why
they're called pink puffers
they stay pink
because they're oxygenating
because they can
overcome that obstruction
but they have that
particular pursed lip
appearance
now of course this requires
a tremendous amount
of work
they've got to breathe
slowly
and breathe in a very
mechanical way
or you know
in a very particular way
and that requires
basically exercise
and so they lose weight
and classically
you'll recall
that these patients
they're very very thin
and then the final change
that we're going to see
in these patients
is that there's going
to be an increased
AP diameter
of the chest
this is super high yield
as well
let me remind you
from normal physiology
that the tendency
of the lung
is to collapse in
the alveoli
have elastic recoil
and they would like
to collapse in
and the tendency
of the chest wall
is to expand out
and so normally
the collapsing
in tendency
of the lung
is in balance
with the expanding
out desire
of the chest wall
now do you know
that point
those two meet
so there's two curves
and those two curves
meet at a particular point
which board examiners
love to ask you
what's that set point
called
that set point
is called
the functional residual
capacity
or the FRC
imagine if a patient
has emphysema
they've lost the elastic
recoil of the lung
correct
so now
the chest wall
is going to win
that tug of war
and it's going to be able
to expand out
a little more
and when it expands out
of the chest
and so this is a classic
finding
in patients
with emphysema
that they have an increased
AP diameter
of the chest
now let me remind you
because examiners
will ask you this
trying to tie in
a little bit of physiology
that when you lose
this elastic recoil
of the lung
and the chest goes out
a little bit
you're going to reset
the FRC
or the functional residual
capacity
so that the FRC
will now be increased
similarly I'll just
give you another example
because it's a board point
that comes up
it's a derivative
of this discussion
if I had fibrosis
of the lung
I would increase
the elastic recoil
of the lung
and therefore I would
actually pull the chest
wall in a little bit
and that would decrease
for example
the FRC
or the functional residual
capacity
here's a picture
of barrel chesting
you can clearly see
that this sort of
looks like a barrel
but most importantly
you've got an increase
in the AP diameter
of the chest
a few late complications
of emphysema
the first is hypoxemia
now basically
these are pink puffers
and they're able
to maintain
gas exchange
appropriately
because they keep
their lips pursed
and they breathe slowly
with prolonged expiration
however
eventually imagine
if these are all
the air sacs
and we're destroying
these air sacs
what's going to eventually
happen is not only
are you losing
the air sacs
in the recoil
but you're also losing
the capillaries
so over time
as you lose
the capillaries
you're going to lose
the bed
across which you're
having oxygen
exchange occur
and so these patients
will become hypoxemic
which means that
they won't be able
to generate
a good
PAO2
remember the hypoxemia
has a PAO2
less than 60
okay
so that's going to be
a problem
and then of course
another problem
as I've already discussed
is eventually
if they get hypoxemia
then the blood vessels
are going to constrict
and as the blood vessels
constrict the right heart
pump against those
blood vessels
and when the right heart
pumps against those
blood vessels
it will first
undergo hypertrophy
but then eventually
it will undergo
failure
and that's called
core pulmonale
I've already explained
this previously
alright
so the next of the COPDs
is asthma
and what I'd like
to say about asthma
is that this is
a chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease
because you get
airway bronchoconstriction
we're all familiar
with asthma
that we recognize
that this is the key
feature of the disease
of course this is
reversible
and of course
what induces
the asthmatic attack
is usually
exposure to
an allergic stimulus
resulting in a
type 1 hypersensitivity
reaction
now asthma presents
in childhood
and it's most often
associated with
other types of
allergic conditions
like allergic rhinitis
eczema
and often
there's a family history
of these types
of atopic reactions
the pathogenesis
of the disease
is that the patient
gets exposed
now this is going to be
a genetically
susceptible patient
alright
so some patient
that's got a family
history and carries
a set of genes
that are going to
make them susceptible
to the development
of asthma
now this patient
they get exposed
to an allergen
that allergen
induces the Th2
phenotype
in C4 positive T cells
which then results
in the T cells
between IL-4
IL-5
and IL-10
remember that
you need to know
for examination
purposes
that the classic
cytokines produced
by the Th2
helper cells
subtype
is IL-4
5 and 10
so 4, 5, 10
that's what I remember
now when I think
about IL-4
you need to know
what it does
and the key thing
that it's going to do
is it is going to
allow the plasma cell
to class switch
to IgE
so it allows for
the production of IgE
and that IgE
is going to be important
as we're all aware of
and IgE is going to
mediate it
as we're going to
talk about
on the next slide
you need to know
that IL-5
is important
for calling in
eosinophils
this is all over
examinations
IL-5 calls in
eosinophils
so that's important
to know
now what does IL-10
do?
well IL-10
it has the ability
to inhibit the production
of Th1 helper T cells
and instead
to induce the production
of Th2 helper T cells
so basically
it helps to promote
this overall reaction
so IL-10
again it stimulates
Th2 subtype
of helper T cells
and inhibits
the Th1 subtype
of helper T cells
now these patients
what will happen
eventually
is that they will get
re-exposed
to the allergen
and when they get
re-exposed to the allergen
remember that these
are the patient's
mass cells
and the mass cells
are going to have
surface IgE
is going to cross-link
that surface IgE
so that when
when surface IgE
molecules get
cross-linked
that's going to activate
the mass cell
very high yield to know
for the purposes
of board examination
what exactly
is going to happen
when the mass cell
is activated
so when the mass cell
the very first thing
that it does
is it dumps
pre-formed histamine
granules
those are released
remember from immunology
and from chapter
from an earlier chapter
in our discussion
that when you release
those pre-formed
histamine granules
that's going to result
in histamine induced
vasodilation
and histamine induced
increased vascular
permeability
again high yield
for examination
let me ask you
one more question
since we're on the topic
the histamine induced
vasodilation
remember where does
that occur
at the arterioles
and the leaking
of fluid
where does that occur
in the post capillary
venule
that's high yield
to be familiar with
but I've already taught you
in the lecture
so anyway
the first step
is the activation
of the mast cells
and that's going to result
in dumping
of histamine initially
now the mast cells
then have a second phase
by which they perpetuate
inflammation
very high yield to know
the second phase
by which they perpetuate
inflammation
is production
of leukotrienes
leukotrienes
C4 D4
and E4
now remember that
leukotrienes C4 D4
and E4
they do a couple things
number one
they cause vasoconstriction
they constrict the smooth muscle
of the blood vessels
increase vascular permeability
by constricting the pericytes
and they cause
bronchoconstriction
by constricting
the smooth muscle
of the bronchus
and if you go back
to your inflammation lectures
I summarized how
leukotrienes work
in a very simple way
and hopefully you'll keep that
in the back of your mind
anyway the point is
that the dumping of
leukotrienes C4 D4
and E4
which again is an arachidonic
acid metabolite
will eventually result
in bronchoconstriction
so that is going to be
the very first phase
which is the activation
of the mast cells
is then going to result
in bronchoconstriction
now over time
what's going to happen
is that
the tissue damage
and the inflammation
and the presence
of inflammatory mediators
like major basic protein
from the eosinophils
is going to perpetuate
bronchoconstriction
and that's the late phase
of the asthma
that's the late phase
of the bronchoconstriction
clinically
these patients
are going to present
with dyspnea
and wheezing
alright
maybe I should take a step
back and remind you
that the clinical features
are episodic
they're basically
in relation to exposure
to the antigen
or the allergic stimulus
and it's going to result
in the classic findings
of shortness of breath
and wheezing
the patient's cough
it's a productive cough
and remember that
the productive cough
contains these spirals
within the mucus
called Kirschmann spirals
and maybe even more important
and more high yield
than that
is that within the mucus
you're going to find
Charcol-Liden crystals
are crystalline aggregates
of eosinophil
major basic protein
and it's those crystalline
aggregates
that can show up
in the mucus
and they're called
Charcol-Liden crystals
and it's a relatively
high yield concept
and I'll show you a picture
in just a moment
now the last thing
I would like to say
is that sometimes patients
can get such a severe attack
that the bronchoconstriction
will not relieve itself
and that severe attack
can actually result
in something called
status asthmaticus
which is the sort of
the most extreme form
of asthma
which can eventually
result in death
now here is a classic picture
of an asthmatic
productive cough
so this is the material
coughed up
put on a slide
and we can clearly see
that there are
these crystals
called Charcol-Liden crystals
which again
are derived from eosinophils
and examiners love
to show pictures like this
the last thing I should say
about asthma
is that there are also
some non-allergic
causes of asthma
for example exercise
some patients will say
that exercise
gives them asthma
other patients might say
that a viral infection
would give them asthma
some patients will say
that when they go to work
they get exposed
to certain dust
and that causes asthma
so these are some
other causes of asthma
asthma is not always
allergic
one very high yield
cause of asthma
to be familiar with
is aspirin
now let me remind you
that there are
a subset of patients
I think it's like
ten to fifteen percent
of adult patients
with asthma
who have something called
aspirin intolerant asthma
so they have asthma
and that's the first part
of the triad
but they also have
this funny thing
where they actually get
bronchospasm
so that's a second feature
of this disease
it's aspirin induced
bronchospasm
and the third feature
is nasal polyps
and that's an interesting
feature
also seen in
aspirin intolerant asthma
let's just talk about
nasal polyps for a second
now nasal polyps
when you think about them
remember from
earlier in this chapter
that you know
you classically see
a nasal polyp
in a patient with
chronic rhinitis
which is inflammation
of the sinonasal mucosa
however there are some
other high yield associations
with nasal polyp
for example
an adult with nasal polyp
with asthma
like symptoms
you think about
aspirin intolerant asthma
so that's one
important association
another very high yield
association
is that if you have a child
like a two year old
with nasal polyps
what do you have to think about
cystic fibrosis
that's high yield
patients actually
who have nasal polyps
need to be tested
for cystic fibrosis
at that age
so that's another important
thing to be aware of
anyway that concludes
our discussion of asthma
now the fourth and final COPD
is actually bronchiectasis
what is bronchiectasis
this is a dilatation
of the bronchioles
and the bronchi
so these are the larger airways
and it's a loss of tone
that results in ear trapping
again let's explain
what happens in this
particular disease
is that the patient
has an airway
this is the normal
and when you have
these airways
the problem in bronchiectasis
is going to be that
you get abnormal dilation
of the airway
now when there's abnormal
dilation of these large airways
that results in loss of
airway tone
and air trapping
perhaps the easiest way
to understand this
is if I gave you a straw
and I asked you to blow
through the straw
and I put my hand
on the other side
I would clearly be able
to feel the air coming out
if I gave you a pipe
bigger than the size
of your face
and I asked you to blow out
I would not feel any air
coming out the other side
and that's because
as air would be accelerated
it would begin to sort of
just whirl around in this tube
and wouldn't be able
to be accelerated
out towards the other end
and that's exactly what happens
in bronchiectasis
this dilation of these airways
results in loss of tone
and that then results
in air trapping
so that when these patients
blow out
they can't get air out
appropriately
they're obstructed
from emptying the lung
here's a classic image
of bronchiectasis
and the idea here
is the following
when you look at the lung
you normally should see
some larger airways
in the center of the lung
because that's where
the large airways are
however when you come out
to the periphery
here is normal
you don't see those large airways
here is where the bronchiectasis is
and notice that
at the edge of the lung
I'm seeing these large
dilated circular air spaces
so that is classic bronchiectasis
the next question is
why do we get this
this dilatation of the airways
and the answer is
it's usually due to
necrotizing inflammation
with damage to the airway wall
so for example
this will occur in patients
who have some reason
to have chronic inflammation
and infection
within the airway
which is then going to result
in damage to the wall
which then dilates the airway
classic example
cystic fibrosis
you know that in cystic fibrosis
patients have thick secretions
the thick secretions
cause mucus plugging
the mucus plugging
increases the risk of infection
because you've blocked a tube
and when you get infection
you're going to get damage
to the airway
and so eventually
you're going to get bronchiectasis
and cystic fibrosis patients
classically have bronchiectasis
another case
where we might see this
is Cartagener syndrome
in Cartagener syndrome
the idea here
is that you have a defect
in what
I think every medical student
is usually able to say cilia
but you need to take it
one step further
what part of the cilia
is defective
ok it's the dianine arm
the dianine arm
which is one component
of the cilia
is defective
and that is necessary
for ciliary movement
so that's Cartagener syndrome
now where would be classic
what would be the symptoms
of this
you get sinusitis
because the cilia
of the respiratory epithelium
in the sinuses
is not functioning properly
so you get inflammation there
the patients get infertility
because the cilia of the sperm
is not functioning properly
they get something called
situs inverses
which is where
the organs that are normally
present on one side
of the thorax
are on the opposite side
so for example
the heart instead of being
on the left
is on the right side
so that's Cartagener syndrome
at the same time
they're going to get
inflammation
and infection
within the lung
and that's because
they don't have the cilia
to pump the mucus
out of the lung
to clear the lung
and so therefore
there's going to be
an increased risk of
infection and inflammation
so that's the second
classic patient
who might get bronchiectasis
a third patient
would be tumor
or foreign body
here's the airways
here's another airway
if there's a foreign body
in the airway
that's going to result
in inflammation
and infection down here
if there's a block
in the tumor
so that compresses
the airway
that would also increase
the risk of infection
and inflammation
any type of
necrotizing infection
if the patient
gets infected
with a bug
that is particularly
necrotizing
and virulent
that could result
in bronchiectasis
and finally
something called
allergic bronchopulmonary
aspergillosis
okay allergic
tells us that
this is a hypersensitivity
reaction
bronchopulmonary
tells us that
it's in the relatively
large airways
and aspergillus
implies that
it's due to aspergillus
now basically
this is a hypersensitivity
reaction
to aspergillus
it is seen
classically in two
patients
do you know which two
it's seen in asthmatics
and it's seen in patients
with cystic fibrosis
and
these patients
become hypersensitive
to aspergillus
when the aspergillus
comes in
from the outside environment
it elicits this reaction
which then damages
the airways
resulting in
a
bronchiectasis
due to the
inflammatory damage
to the airway
so that's
ABPA
allergic bronchopulmonary
aspergillosis
clinically
these patients
are going to have
cough
because again
these large airways
are going to result
in
this dilatation
of the large airways
is also going to result
in some mucus trapping
so they'll cough up
that mucus
they'll have dyspnea
difficulty breathing
and foul smelling sputum
now that sputum
that comes out
is going to be loaded
with inflammatory junk
and will have been
sitting in the lung
for a while
and rotting
so it'll smell very bad
complications include
hypoxemia
there's going to be
trapping of carbon dioxide
eventually the patients
will get hypoxemia
and a complication of that
would be
corpulmonale
I've already covered that
what's important to note
here is that these patients
can also develop
a secondary amyloidosis
very high yield
for exams
can we remind ourselves
for a moment
just go back
and let's do a quick
amyloidosis refers to
the deposition of a
misfolded protein
that's point one
point two
amyloidosis can be
localized or systemic
localized means that
the amyloid deposits
in one organ
systemic means that
the amyloid deposits
in multiple organs
now if the amyloid
deposits in multiple organs
i.e. systemic
it can be primary
or secondary
in primary amyloidosis
you have a deposition
of amyloid light chain
due to some sort of
plasma cell problem
the plasma cells
overproduce light chain
into the blood
it deposits in tissues
as amyloid
in secondary amyloidosis
you have chronic
inflammation
which produces an
acute phase reactant
called SAA
that's overproduced
in chronic inflammation
that chronic
that overproduction
of SAA gets converted
to AA
and it's AA
that deposits
as amyloid
and that's called
secondary amyloidosis
so these patients
would have secondary
amyloidosis
with deposition
of AA amyloid
and that concludes
our section on COPD
very high yield
a lot of physiology
but very important
to be aware
of these diseases